<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Projects | Gerard Condon's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/categories/projects/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-04T23:16:10+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerard Condon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Side Project: Irish Rail Tracker]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2013/03/18/side-project-irish-rail-tracker/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T10:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2013/03/18/side-project-irish-rail-tracker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been working on a <a href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/projects/irishrail/index.html">side project</a> for the last month in order to learn about front-end web development. While not complete by any means, I think it's good enough to release as a beta. I plan to add features, improve the UI and refactor the code in future.</p>

<p>The motivation behind it was that I wanted to do a project using one of the JavaScript <a href="http://addyosmani.github.com/todomvc/">MVC Frameworks</a> - for this one I chose <a href="http://backbonejs.org">Backbone</a>. Also I'll be working more with HTML and CSS in work over the coming year and I need to ramp up on these.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.irishrail.ie">Iarnród Éireann</a> (the Irish Rail company) has a REST API which provides details of the stations in its network and the current status of its trains. My <a href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/projects/irishrail/index.html">webpage</a> plots these stations and trains on a Google Map and shows upcoming train information for each station.</p>

<p>I plan to write a series of posts on how I implemented this and the lessons I learned along the way.</p>

<p>The project is available <a href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/projects/irishrail/index.html">here</a> and the code is available on <a href="https://github.com/gerardcondon/Irish-Rail-Tracker">Github</a> under the MIT licence. The roadmap.md document is where I'm tracking future work that needs to be done on the project. Any feedback would be much appreciated.</p>

<p>As far as the code goes:</p>

<ul>
<li>I'm happy enough with the Backbone model and collection code. The Backbone view code still needs some refactoring to remove duplication and use proper Backbone idioms.</li>
<li>There are some JavaScript <a href="http://pivotal.github.com/jasmine/">Jasmine</a> tests - mostly for the model. I'm still figuring out the best way to test the UI - I have some Jasmine tests but also some Ruby <a href="https://github.com/jnicklas/capybara">Capybara</a> tests for the browser.</li>
<li>The HTML and CSS code are functional rather than elegant. I'm hoping to improve these as time goes by and as I get more experience with these languages.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
