<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Gerard Condon's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-05-19T18:00:51+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerard Condon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Localizing iOS Apps]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/05/19/localizing-ios-apps/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-19T16:54:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/05/19/localizing-ios-apps</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was looking at a tutorial for creating a settings bundle for my app and it had separate files for different languages. I realised that I hadn&#8217;t a clue how to localize iOS applications. I decided I&#8217;d better look into it now, rather than at the end of development, in case it required me to change existing code. Much better to implement with localization in mind, than retrofit at the end of development.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m interested to see how many translations I&#8217;ll be able to include in the app. I&#8217;m not sure how easy it will be to do the translation or even how much text there will be to translate. I&#8217;m planning a Chinese translation and for sentimental reasons I&#8217;ll do an Irish translation. I&#8217;ll probably try to get some European languages done also. I think that once I put in the infrastructure to do one language then adding additional ones shouldn&#8217;t be too much bother.</p>

<p>The basics of implementing localization is that you externalize all strings in your application to .strings files and then provide versions of these files for each language you support. The process for creating the basic localization.strings file is outlined <a href="http://userflex.wordpress.com/2011/10/20/localized-strings-xcode4/">here</a>. In your code you can get the localized values for these strings using NSLocalizedString(@&#8221;Externalized String Name&#8221;, @&#8221;&#8220;).</p>

<h2>Localization Tools</h2>

<p>Using this method, we will have to deal with lots of .strings files. Xcode doesn&#8217;t provide much help here so I looked around for third party apps. I bought <a href="http://www.cocoanetics.com/apps/linguan/">Linguan</a> on the Mac App Store and it looks very good. You point it at an Xcode project file and it locates all the .strings files and presents them in a nice table. It can generate text files which you can send on to your translators for them to translate and re-import their translations. I&#8217;m very pleased with it so far.</p>

<p>Apart from having .strings files for strings in the code, I also need to localize the app&#8217;s storyboards. Albert Mata has a fantastic tutorial on how to do this <a href="http://www.albertmata.net/articles/introduction-to-internationalization-using-storyboards-on-ios-5.html">here</a>. A big problem with localizing storyboards is that changes in one language&#8217;s storyboards are not propagated to the others. Manually keeping these in sync would be a nightmare. Thankfully there is a handy script <a href="http://code.google.com/p/edim-mobile/source/browse/trunk/ios/IncrementalLocalization/localize.py">here</a> by Ederson Machado, which will update the .strings files for the storyboard and also keep the storyboards in sync. There is a nice video outlining the features of the script <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cF1Rf02QvZQ">here</a>. By adding this script as a build run script, we can ensure that our storyboards are always in sync.</p>

<h2>Localization Workflow</h2>

<p>My localization workflow is as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li>First I created multiple storyboards for each language using the Localization area on the sidebar. This will create a language.proj folder for each language.</li>
<li>I ran the localize.py script on the project. This generated the mainstoryboard.strings files in each of the language folders.</li>
<li>I manually add these files to Xcode. First I added the English version. Then I clicked the plus button in the Localization sidebar and added the other languages. Xcode is able to find those .strings files and link them to the overall file.</li>
<li>I create a localization.strings file to deal with the strings in the code and added all languages.</li>
<li>I ran genstrings but I don&#8217;t think this is needed if you&#8217;re using Linguan.</li>
<li>When I opened the project in Linguan it was able to find all the strings files, including those from the storyboard.</li>
</ul>


<p>I&#8217;m satisfied now that I have the localization mostly under control. One thing I still need to look at is how does this affect testing. Hopefully any test framework that I used will be able to run the tests in all languages.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting out with Core Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/05/15/starting-with-core-data/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-15T21:59:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/05/15/starting-with-core-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For my project, I need a way to store the model data that I will be generating. I certainly don&#8217;t want to write a persistence layer for my model objects so I will definitely use a standard library for this. There are a number of options</p>

<ul>
<li>Core Data. This provides an editor to create the objects and XCode will generate the required model classes for me.</li>
<li>Use a database like Sqlite directly. Core Data uses a sqlite database behind the scenes but instead I could create one directly and access it using a library like <a href="https://github.com/ccgus/fmdb">FMVH</a>.</li>
<li>A service like <a href="http://www.parse.com">Parse.com</a>. This provides an online backend for apps.</li>
</ul>


<p>I don&#8217;t want to use the database directly as I prefer working with objects, so that would rule out sqlite for me. Parse.com is really interesting. Among other things, it provides an online site where you can see the data in a spreadsheet interface. This <a href="http://houseofbilz.com/archives/2011/11/30/an-example-backboneparse-com-app/">tutorial</a> shows how you can use Parse.com to implement a todo list website. It&#8217;s a real pity that iCloud doesn&#8217;t provide a similar API to allow non-Apple devices access the data.</p>

<p>In the end I&#8217;ve decided to go with Core Data. The reasons for this are</p>

<ul>
<li>It&#8217;s an Apple standard library and one of the purposes of writing an app was to learn about iOS and Apple technologies. Where possible I&#8217;ve tried to stick to the Apple way of doing things as I can be sure that this approach will be supported in future - or if there is a new system, then a transition path will be provided.</li>
<li>Core Data works on the object level rather than the database level. I&#8217;ve programmed in objects for most of my career so this is familiar to me. I have a working knowledge of databases but I feel more comfortable using OOP.</li>
<li>I&#8217;m assuming that Core Data should integrate with iCloud better than other approaches. Thinking ahead I&#8217;d like to look at iCloud at some stage and learning Core Data first should make that a bit easier.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Magical Record and Mogenerator</h2>

<p>There are some good Core Data tutorials out there. The best introduction that I found was the <a href="http://www.stanford.edu/class/cs193p/cgi-bin/drupal/downloads-2011-fall">Stanford</a> iOS course (lectures 13 &amp; 14). To be honest, the code required to implement Core Data is fairly complex and verbose. To deal with that, I started looking for libraries which would improve the Core Data experience. The best I found is <a href="https://github.com/magicalpanda/MagicalRecord">Magical Record</a>. This library simplifies Core Data a great deal and provides loads of helper categories &amp; functions. There is an excellent tutorial on MagicalRecord <a href="http://yannickloriot.com/2012/03/magicalrecord-how-to-make-programming-with-core-data-pleasant/">here</a>. I also found <a href="http://ablfx.com/blog/?post_type=post&amp;p=561">this</a> tutorial really good and it also includes a sample project which uses MagicalRecord.</p>

<p>Magical Record works well with another tool called <a href="https://github.com/rentzsch/mogenerator">Mogenerator</a>. You download a .dmg from the site and install from that. There is a nice tutorial <a href="http://raptureinvenice.com/getting-started-with-mogenerator/">here</a>. Mogenerator generates classes from the Core Data xcdatamodel file. The normal Core Data build can also do this but the advantage of Mogenerator is that it generates a second set of classes for each Core Data entity. This second set will never be overwritten so you can write custom code in these. The first set of classes will be regenerated each time the model gets updated.</p>

<p>Magical Record is available on Github. Like most iOS projects I&#8217;ve found there, it seems the standard way to integrate this with your project is to copy the source files into your code and work away. I&#8217;m not too comfortable with this approach and would prefer to keep third party libraries separate from my code. This would allow me to update these independently and share them between projects. I&#8217;ll have to look into what options are available for this.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joined the iOS Developer program]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/04/29/joined-the-ios-developer-program/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-29T21:40:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/04/29/joined-the-ios-developer-program</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve been fairly busy with the Start Your Own Business course so I haven&#8217;t had much time to do iOS programming. It&#8217;s time to get back into it now though, and so I&#8217;ve just paid my subscription to the iOS developer program. I&#8217;m looking forward to being able to run code on an actual device. It&#8217;s been a bit limiting working on just the simulator and there&#8217;s nothing like seeing your code running on the final hardware.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Where have all the SRPGs gone]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/04/02/where-have-all-the-srpgs-gone/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-02T00:27:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/04/02/where-have-all-the-srpgs-gone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had a draft post pre-written earlier this year lamenting the decline of the SRPG game genre. In brief, I used to import these types of games all the time from America for my PS2. I assumed that this would continue for the PS3 and really enjoyed <a href="http://www.eurogamer.net/games/valkyria-chronicles-ps3">Valkyria Chronicles</a>, but after that the genre has pretty much disappeared for the mainstream consoles. Even on PSN and Xbox live, there has been very little released (<a href="http://www.eurogamer.net/articles/vandal-hearts-flames-of-judgment-review">Vandal Hearts</a> excepted). Modern games seemed to be limited more and more to mass market genres such as the 3D first person shooter.</p>

<p>However in the past month a surprising new development in game development has kind of invalidated my draft post. Veteran game designers have started to use Kickstarter to seek funding for niche game genres with some amazing results. The first big <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/66710809/double-fine-adventure">success</a> on Kickstarter was Tim Schafer, Ron Gilbert and Double Fine raising over three million to make a new adventure game. I love the Monkey Island games so I backed this - it was actually the first thing I&#8217;d ever supported on Kickstarter. I have no idea if the game will be any good but given the caliber of the people involved, I think it&#8217;s in safe hands. To be honest, the videos they&#8217;ve made for the project have been worth the cash already.</p>

<p>Following on from that Brian Fargo launched a <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/inxile/wasteland-2">Wasteland 2</a> project. This is an attempt to revive the party based CRPGs. This was another genre that I really enjoyed and which stagnated recently. Today&#8217;s publishers aren&#8217;t willing to put up the cash for these games. I&#8217;ve started to contribute to more of these gaming projects on Kickstarter (including a space based game - <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/64409699/ftl-faster-than-light">FTL</a> and a Norse SRPG - <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/projects/stoic/the-banner-saga">The Banner Saga</a>). Hopefully this will show that there is a sizable market for these games and they will be more likely to be funded in future. It&#8217;s really interesting how much more invested in the games you feel once you back them on Kickstarter. For example, I&#8217;m really enjoying reading the updates from the game developers. If I was an indie developer I would definitely go down this route. The community that the Kickstarter project creates for your game might be as important as the funding itself.</p>

<p>Another other thing this has made me realize is how much reputation and track record matters. I had never heard of Wasteland 2 before backing it. However once Brian Fargo reeled off the list of games that he&#8217;d worked on, i.e. Fallout, Baldur&#8217;s Gate and Icewind Dale (all of which still sit proudly on my shelf), I had no hesitation in subscribing. I would much rather see people like him develop games instead of leaving it in the hands of companies like Zynga. Trying to learn from this, I think that having a portfolio would be really valuable for a software engineer. Imagine the kind of CV/resume you&#8217;d have if you developed one app, website or side project per year and hosted these online. Given the frameworks and services that are out there e.g. <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Rails</a>, <a href="http://www.parse.com">Parse.com</a>, <a href="http://www.heroku.com">Heroku</a> for the web, iOS and Android for mobile, I think it&#8217;s never been easier to create quality small scale projects. To be honest I wish I had started something like that years ago. If I was coming out of college now, one of the first things I&#8217;d do would be to register my name as a url and start hosting projects there. It&#8217;s something small but would really pay off down the line.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Start your own Business Course]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/03/20/start-your-own-business-course/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-20T23:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/03/20/start-your-own-business-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve signed up for a Start Your Own Business <a href="http://www.sceb.ie/Online-Booking#Start-Your-Own-Business">course</a> which is being run by the <a href="http://www.sceb.ie">South Cork Enterprise Board</a>. It&#8217;s an eight week course taking three hours every Thursday. I&#8217;ve no intention of leaving my current job but if I&#8217;m going to be doing this on the side, then I&#8217;d like to know how to do it properly and what type of supports are out there.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve gone to three nights already and I&#8217;m finding it very useful. I think that the process of creating a business plan focuses your mind on what you want to achieve. I&#8217;ve asked myself more questions about what I want to do with this app development in the past few weeks than in the previous two months. It&#8217;s also interesting meeting people there who are setting up non software businesses and seeing what common problems and tasks we have. It&#8217;s good to step outside the software/computing world for a bit and get a wider perspective on things. I hope to come out of this with a clear idea of where I want to take the app work and what I need to do to accomplish this.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up a Blog on Octopress and Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/03/04/setting-up-octopress-and-github/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-04T13:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/03/04/setting-up-octopress-and-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post documents how I migrated the blog from <a href="http://www.wordpress.com">Wordpress.com</a> to <a href="http://www.octopress.org">Octopress</a>. There are a number of bloggers who have written about switching their blogs to Octopress. I found these posts very helpful - <a href="http://scottmuc.com/migrated-to-octopress/">Scott Muc</a>, <a href="http://mattgemmell.com/2011/09/12/blogging-with-octopress/">Matt Gemmell</a> and <a href="http://blog.bigdinosaur.org/setting-up-octopress/">Bigdinosaur Blog</a>. The basic sequence of steps I followed was</p>

<ul>
<li>Install Ruby.</li>
<li>Install Octopress.</li>
<li>Create account on <a href="http://www.github.com">Github</a>.</li>
<li>Export previous blog from Wordpress and convert it to Markdown</li>
<li>Generate Octopress blog and publish it to Github.</li>
<li>In parallel I registered www.gerardcondon.com and set it up so that it pointed to the blog on Github.</li>
<li>Setup a drafts folder on Dropbox so that I can write posts from anywhere.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Ruby Setup</h2>

<p>The first step is to install <a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</a>. If you want to, you can compile this from the source but the better option is to use a third party tool to install and manage Ruby. The one I used is <a href="https://rvm.beginrescueend.com/rvm/install/">RVM</a>.</p>

<p>By default OS X Lion comes with 1.8.7 pre-installed but Octopress needs 1.9.2. (I tried 1.9.3 at first but Octopress reported an error). I read on Stack Overflow that it&#8217;s not recommended to upgrade the default installation but instead to install the newer version alongside it. RVM is designed to manage multiple versions of Ruby on a system so it&#8217;s a nice fit here.</p>

<p>The command to install Ruby is <code>rvm install 1.9.2</code>. However when I tried this I got errors complaining that the C compiler was LLVM based instead of gcc. To get around this I added the following flag <code>rvm install 1.9.2 --with-gcc=clang</code>. Now we can tell RVM to use version 1.9.2 with this command <code>rvm use 1.9.2</code>.</p>

<h2>Install Octopress</h2>

<p>Installing Octopress is very easy once Ruby is installed. The instructions can be found at <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/setup/">Octopress Setup</a>. The install command is <code>rake install</code> and then to build your website run <code>rake generate</code>. Octopress takes whatever pages and posts it finds under the source folder and builds these to a static website. These need to have particular file names and contents, so Octopress provides helper commands to generate a new post or page. These are <code>rake new_page["page_title"]</code> and <code>rake new_post["post_title"]</code> respectively.</p>

<h2>Export from Wordpress</h2>

<p>To export from Wordpress I simply used their export tool. This exported all the posts in their own html files. This would have been fine for Octopress but I wanted the whole site in Markdown, so I converted each post from html to markdown and added to the source/_posts folder.</p>

<h2>Host on Github</h2>

<p>Once you have the Octopress blog created you need to host it somewhere. I choose Github as it provides for free hosting of static blogs. Also if I do release some iOS code later it will be on Github, so there&#8217;s no harm in getting it set up now.</p>

<p>This <a href="http://code.dblock.org/octopress-setting-up-a-blog-and-contributing-to-an-existing-one">site</a> has a very good explanation of what is going on with Github. Basically we build our website locally to a folder named public. We create a repository on Github for our webpage. Octopress then uploads the contents of the public folder to the master branch on this repository whenever we run the <code>rake deploy</code> command. It is recommended that you upload the site source to a source branch on the repository. That way you can always regenerate the website even if you delete the local files.</p>

<h2>Register URL</h2>

<p>I decided to register www.gerardcondon.com for this site as I didn&#8217;t want to be tied to a Github url in the same way as I was tied to the Wordpress.com one. I didn&#8217;t need hosting or anything special - just forwarding. I used <a href="http://www.namecheap.com">Namecheap</a>. The price is really cheap for a .com address - only 6 or 7 dollars a year.</p>

<p>There are instructions on <a href="http://pages.github.com">Github Pages</a> on how to set up the forwarding. You need to setup an A record to redirect to www.github.com for your url without the www part, i.e. gerardcondon.com will redirect to www.github.com. Then you need to create a CNAME file in github and then setup a CNAME redirect for the www part of the url, i.e. www.gerardcondon.com redirects to gerardcondon.github.com. However I ran into some problems doing this on the namecheap site. When I tried to setup the CNAME I got the following errors</p>

<p><code>Improper records were NOT saved!</code>
<code>There were issues with some records and they were either set to default or completely removed. Please review the issues below and update again appropriately.</code>
<code>INVALID_ADDR: 'gerardcondon.github.com/' should not be an IP/ URL for CNAME record. (host name: www)</code></p>

<p>However I just connected to the online chat support and the person assigned to me fixed it up in a few minutes - I have to say they were really helpful. This DNS stuff takes a while to settle down - I think it was a day or so before it had propagated out. Since then I&#8217;ve had no trouble with it.</p>

<h2>Octopress tweaks</h2>

<p>I&#8217;ve made a few tweaks to Octopress to suit my own tastes.</p>

<ul>
<li>I changed the indented-lists setting to true in sass/custom/_layout.scss. Previously the numbers and bullets for lists were not in line with the rest of the post text but instead were placed in the left margin.</li>
<li>I reduced the size of the blockquotes in the sass/base/_typography.scss file, from 1.2 em down to 1 em to be the same size as normal text.</li>
<li>I changed the solarized theme from dark to light in sass/base/_solarized.scss.</li>
</ul>


<p>It&#8217;s really easy to make changes to Octopress, there is a folder called sass with most of the style stuff. There are a few configuration files also which can be updated. One nice thing about checking all this stuff into github is that you can go back and see what style updates you made in previous commits.</p>

<h2>Add Draft folder and sync with Dropbox</h2>

<p>At this stage Octopress was installed on my Macbook Air and working perfectly for me. One limitation of this setup was that I could only edit posts from that machine. I didn&#8217;t mind only being able to regenerate the site from the Air as that&#8217;s not a common task, but I wanted to be able to write posts from anywhere. I also wanted the ability to write draft posts and not have Octopress automatically publish those.</p>

<p>I found a technique for managing draft posts on <a href="http://www.i-m-code.com/blog/blog/2012/01/25/target-any-deployment-environment-in-octopress-with-ease/">Frozen Bytes</a>. This allows you to create a drafts folder and provides commands for moving posts between the draft and published state.</p>

<p>Using this, I created a folder called drafts in Dropbox. I then symlinked to this from inside the sources directory on the Air. All my drafts are now available in Dropbox and I can edit these anywhere. This is especially useful when editing from iOS as there are a number of markdown editors which can edit files on Dropbox.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>I think that&#8217;s everything! It was fairly straightforward in retrospect to set up. The new setup works really well. I&#8217;m very happy with the look of Octopress and the editing workflow in markdown is much better than using the Wordpress editor. Looking forward to using it in future.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OS X Mountain Lion]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/22/os-x-mountain-lion/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-22T00:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/22/os-x-mountain-lion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apple has just announced <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/mountain-lion">Mountain Lion</a>, the latest update to OS X, and it looks to have some interesting features. The main one I&#8217;m looking forward to is the addition of <a href="http://www.apple.com/macosx/mountain-lion/features.html#airplay">AirPlay</a> to the Mac. I love being able to stream video from the iPhone to the Apple TV. It&#8217;s really handy for the iTunes U lectures. However for normal videos that I have on the Mac, it&#8217;s annoying to have to convert them via <a href="http://www.inmethod.com/forum/posts/list/4529.page">Air Video Server</a> on the Mac and then use <a href="http://www.inmethod.com/air-video/index.html">Air Video</a> on the iPhone to get them to display on the Apple TV. Having AirPlay on the Mac stream directly to the Apple TV will be very handy. According to the docs, it&#8217;s just for streaming applications and presentations but perhaps they will open it up to interactive applications in future. I wonder what the latency would be like on this and if eventually it would be possible to play games via the Apple TV.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m finding that as I integrate more and more Apple devices into my setup, they all make each other work better. AirPlay is one example of this. Another is iTunes match which really starts to excel when you have multiple devices. Previously it was impossible to keep multiple iTunes in sync. It was a nightmare trying to add new music as it had to be added to each library separately. Now my music library is always in sync everywhere and when I add music to one library, it gets uploaded and is available on all others immediately. I haven&#8217;t always been too impressed with Apple&#8217;s cloud services (i.e. MobileMe was a bit of a disaster) but they&#8217;ve got it right with iTunes Match.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Coverage Updates for Xcode 4.3]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/21/code-coverage-updates-for-xcode-4-dot-3/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-21T00:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/21/code-coverage-updates-for-xcode-4-dot-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a previous <a href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/17/adding-code-coverage-to-unit-tests/">post</a>, I described how I got code coverage up and running in Xcode 4.2. Apple have just released Xcode 4.3 and unfortunatly updating to this has broken my code coverage. The reason is that 4.3 removes the /Developer folder and moves this internally to the Xcode.app package. While this has good consequences - it should be possible to update Xcode from the App Store like a normal app - unfortunately it has also removed the libprofile_rt library from /Developer/usr/lib. I haven&#8217;t been able to find a new version of this library in Xcode 4.3. When I tried using the version from 4.2, I got &#8220;mach-o but wrong architecture&#8221; errors.</p>

<p>This means that when building my unit tests with Coverage I get link errors saying that I am missing llvm_gcda functions (llvm_gcda_start_file, llvm_gcda_increment_indirect_counter, llvm_gcda_emit_function, llvm_gcda_emit_arcs). I searched on Google to try and find a solution for 4.3 but it seemed all solutions were for 4.2 so I needed to try to solve this myself. The solution I came up with is fairly hacky. I&#8217;m hoping that as more people upgrade to 4.3, a better solution will be found and I can switch to that.</p>

<p>My solution is to take the actual file which contained the gcda functions in libprofile_rt, add it to my own source code and compile it myself. The file in question can be found on llvm.org - <a href="https://llvm.org/svn/llvm-project/llvm/trunk/runtime/libprofile/GCDAProfiling.c">here</a>. To get it to build locally I deleted the win32 and sys includes (lines 27 to 31 inclusive) and replaced the llvm include (line 23) with <code>#include "stdint.h"</code>. This builds fine using the Coverage build configuration and outputs the same gcda and gcno files as before. To make sure that this code doesn&#8217;t end up in the released project by accident, I&#8217;ve included it in the unit test bundle rather than the app bundle. This is fine for me as I only need coverage when running the tests anyway.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Some feedback from Tom Black, who emailed me to point out that libprofile_rt can be found in <code>/Applications/Xcode.app/Contents/Developer/Platforms/iPhoneOS.platform/Developer/usr/</code>
However this library did not work for either of us. Instead we got errors like
<code>The bundle “GCUtilsTests.octest” couldn’t be loaded because it is damaged or missing necessary resources.</code>
<code>Library not loaded: @executable_path ... libprofile_rt.dylib</code>
<code>Reason: image not found</code><br/>
Also this library didn&#8217;t produce .gcda files but instead generated .dia files which didn&#8217;t work in Coverflow.</p>

<p>What worked for Tom, but not for me, was not to include libprofile at all. This removed these errors and another incompatible binary error. Now however he got the following error.
<code>Detected an attempt to call a symbol in system libraries that is not present on the iPhone:
fopen$UNIX2003 called from function llvm_gcda_start_file</code>
He found the solution to this issue <a href="http://www.infinite-loop.dk/blog/2012/02/code-coverage-and-fopen-unix2003-problems/">here</a>. I still got link errors when I followed this though so I need to stick with my original solution.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Another commenter Rajiv emailed me to say that creating a new target for his project made the coverage work for him. It generated the .gcda and .gcno files when he exited using exit(0). I&#8217;ve tried creating a new simple iOS app and I don&#8217;t get any errors for this when I enable coverage.</p>

<p>One thing which might explain why it still doesn&#8217;t work for some of my projects is the type of project being built. My original project was a static library. I tried to create a new static library project and when I try to enable coverage I get the same link errors as above.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apple's New Introduction to iOS Development]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/18/apple-new-introduction-to-ios-development/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-18T09:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/18/apple-new-introduction-to-ios-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apple has posted a <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/#referencelibrary/GettingStarted/RoadMapiOS/Introduction/Introduction.html">new guide</a> to iOS development which ties together all the various strands of creating an app. (via <a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/2012/02/17/apple-posts-guide-to-start-developing-ios-apps/">Loop Insight</a>). Looks really nice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding Code Coverage to Unit Tests for Xcode 4.2]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/17/adding-code-coverage-to-unit-tests/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-17T22:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/17/adding-code-coverage-to-unit-tests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are going to the effort of having unit tests, then you really need to have code coverage. This will allow you to ensure that your tests are exercising all your code. It is really easy to spot a missing test when you see a branch of an if-else with no coverage. Code coverage for me is also a way to motivate myself to implement the tests. It&#8217;s like high scores in games - it gives me a target to aim for. Coverage gives feedback that your tests are actually doing something, and with each test you add, you can see the areas of untested code steadily decrease.</p>

<p>To set up code coverage in Xcode 4.2 I used the guide on these blogs - <a href="http://www.infinite-loop.dk/blog/2011/05/covering-it-all-up/">Infinite Loop</a> and <a href="http://mattrajca.com/post/8749868513/llvm-code-coverage-and-xcode-4">Matt Rajca</a>. Originally only the gcc compiler was supported but since then the Clang compiler has had code coverage enabled. This is important as we need to use Clang for ARC and static analysis among other things.</p>

<h3>XCode Build Settings</h3>

<p>Xcode has the concept of build configurations which can have built settings altered independently of each other. The two default configurations are Debug and Release. We want to add a new configuration named Coverage. To do this duplicate the Debug configuration.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.gerardcondon.com/images/codeCoverage/NewBuildConfig.png" title="New Build Configuration" ></p>

<p>In order to specify different settings for configurations in Xcode, hover over the left hand margin directly to the left of the setting we wish to update. An arrow will appear which when clicked will expand to an additional three lines for Debug, Coverage and Release. Editing the top line will alter the setting for all versions. Altering either of the new lines will only update the setting for that version of the build.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.gerardcondon.com/images/codeCoverage/BuildSettings.png" title="Build Settings" ></p>

<ul>
<li>Open the Build Settings tab for the main target. Under &#8220;Apple LLVM 3.0 compiler - Code Generation&#8221;, enable both

<ul>
<li>&#8220;Generate Test Coverage Files&#8221;</li>
<li> &#8220;Instrument Program Flow&#8221;</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> We now need to add the libprofile_rt library to the build. This will link in the implementations of the coverage functions. If you are seeing link errors like &#8220;_llvm_gcda_increment_indirect_counter&#8221;, referenced from:&#8221;, then you have not done this step.<br/>
This library is located in /Developer/usr/lib. This folder contains libprofile.a which is a static library and a libprofile.dylib which is a dynamic linked library (similar to a .dll in Windows). To link this open the Build Phases tab for the main target. Expand the &#8220;Link Binary with Libraries&#8221; and click the + button. Click &#8220;Add Other&#8221; and then find libprofile_rt.dylib in the file viewer and add it. (Note that this doesn&#8217;t work for me since Xcode 4.3. I&#8217;ve documented the updates I needed to make <a href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/21/code-coverage-updates-for-xcode-4-dot-3/">here</a>).</li>
</ul>


<h3>Executing Tests</h3>

<p>Now your unit tests should run and if you examine the build output files under the DerivedData folder you should find .gcda and .gcno coverage files along with your .o files. To find this folder you can go to the Projects tab in the Organizer and select your project. The path to the Derived Data folder is listed here along with an arrow which will open the folder in the Finder.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.gerardcondon.com/images/codeCoverage/DerivedData.png" title="Derived Data" ></p>

<p>From here the path to the coverage files is Build/Intermediates/${Project Target}.build/Coverage-iphonesimulator/${Project Target}.build/Objects-normal/i386. Replace ${Project Target} with the name of your project target.</p>

<h3>Viewing Coverage Data</h3>

<p>To view the coverage data I used <a href="http://code.google.com/p/coverstory/">CoverStory</a>. Simply open the app and point it at the coverage folder. This will give a nice two pane display showing your files on the left and an editor which shows how often each line of code was hit. Now you can identify untested code and add new tests to cover them.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving the blog to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/16/moving-the-blog-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-16T20:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/16/moving-the-blog-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve decided to switch the blog from <a href="http://www.wordpress.com">Wordpress.com</a> to an <a href="http://www.octopress.org">Octopress</a> site hosted on <a href="http://pages.github.com">Github Pages</a>. From now on there will be no more new posts on Wordpress. I&#8217;ve also registered the domain <a href="http://www.gerardcondon.com">gerardcondon.com</a> and will be using this address for the blog in future.</p>

<p>I have a few reasons for switching</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I found Wordpress.com to be an excellent site in general. When starting off it was very easy to create and get the blog up and running. However you have to use their site to create your posts. Even if you use a text editor you still ultimately have to paste the post into their site, and all subsequent edits have to be done through Wordpress.com. Also the definitive version of the posts are stored in their database.</p>

<p>  I prefer to write my documents in plain text files using a markup language. Previously I&#8217;ve used <a href="http://www.latex-project.org/">Latex</a> and more recently I&#8217;ve started using <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>. This has a number of advantages, namely the files can be edited in any editor on any platform and they work very well with source control. Also by separating the content from the typesetting phase, I find that you concentrate better on the actual writing. I hate having to wrestle with formatting in Word; I much prefer leaving that to a program. Donald Knuth &amp; Co. have forgotten more about typesetting than I will ever know.</p>

<p>  Wordpress.com doesn&#8217;t support Markdown so posting involved an extra step of converting the Markdown to HTML. This meant that I had two versions of the blog. One in Markdown on my local machine and another in HTML on Wordpress. For me, it&#8217;s an axiom that whenever you have two versions of the same data, they will get out of sync. One needs to be the main source. I wanted the local Markdown version to be the canonical version of the site and everything else derived from that.</p></li>
<li><p>I think the default Octopress theme looks really good (I really like the Archive page). I first noticed it on <a href="http://www.mattgemmell.com">Matt Gemmell&#8217;s</a> site and was impressed by how it looked. It also looks well on mobile sites. I have full control of the css using Octopress so I can tweak whatever I want. I liked the <a href="http://theme.wordpress.com/themes/titan/">Titan</a> theme on Wordpress except I hated the crosses using for lists. On Wordpress.com there was no way to change these. However on Octopress I make any kind of style update.</p></li>
<li><p>I realised that I should get my own domain name instead of using the Wordpress.com address. In future if I need to move my site I can just redirect the domain name and any old links will still work. Whereas I will never own or control the gerardcondon.wordpress.com links. It&#8217;s better to move now, rather than after I create lots of content at a non portable url. Start as you mean to go on.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>The posting workflow is much better now. I write my posts in Markdown on the Mac or on iOS via <a href="http://www.hogbaysoftware.com/products/writeroom">WriteRoom</a>. Then I run a command from the terminal to regenerate the site and deploy it to Github. Edits work in the same way. The Markdown files also get committed to Github ensuring that no matter where I move the blog in future I will always have the content in an accessible file format.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ll add a few posts in future on how I got Octopress, Github and my domain all set up and working together.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Test Automation]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/13/test-automation/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-13T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/13/test-automation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>  Wherever possible I think that automating your testing is essential. For this project there is no way that I can manually rerun the same tests over and over again - the time commitment is just too much. I need to be able to click a button and have a framework run all my tests automatically and report back to me the number of tests passing, failing etc. I know that this won&#8217;t catch all the bugs in the code and that I&#8217;ll still need to do some manual testing for each release. However, the more I can push into this automated testing, the more time I&#8217;ll save on the manual testing later.</p>

<p>Based on my previous <a href="blog/2012/02/10/devising-my-unit-testing-philosophy/">post</a> I&#8217;ve mentally divided up the code into different layers which build on top of each other. The app GUI is one layer. Then we have the model classes which in turn depend on utility classes etc. These different levels of code require different levels of testing.</p>

<p>  For the utility and model layers I plan to use an automated unit testing framework such as <a href="http://www.junit.org/">JUnit</a>. Xcode provides <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/#documentation/DeveloperTools/Conceptual/UnitTesting/03-Writing_Test_Case_Methods/writing_tests.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40002143-CH4-SW1">OCUnit</a> which is a JUnit like framework for implementing unit tests. This framework provides the usual fail and assert macros and functions. There are some annoying things about running unit tests in Xcode. One is that it doesn&#8217;t have a separate test runner panel like JUnit has in <a href="http://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse</a>. Instead it treats the unit test errors as build failures. All the print output for the tests is dumped into the same console output which can make it tricky to identify which output is for which test. Also there is no way to selectively run these tests. You have to rerun them all together every time. There are other frameworks out there e.g. <a href="https://github.com/gabriel/gh-unit">GHUnit</a> but for the moment I&#8217;ll stick with the default.</p>

<p>For the higher level GUI code, unit testing is not useful so I&#8217;ll need a different testing approach and toolset. There seem to be number of <a href="http://sgleadow.github.com/blog/2011/10/26/which-automated-ios-testing-tool-to-use/">options</a> out there. I&#8217;m not sure what is available and what is the best to use. Apple have an <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/mac/documentation/developertools/conceptual/InstrumentsUserGuide/Built-InInstruments/Built-InInstruments.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40004652-CH6-SW75">Instruments</a> application which allows you do perform UI testing using Javascript. I&#8217;ve also seen these <a href="http://www.testingwithfrank.com/">Frank</a> and <a href="http://www.zucchiniframework.org/">Zucchini</a> frameworks. I haven&#8217;t evaluated any of these yet as I don&#8217;t have a fully functional app to test it on. Once I get a nearly complete app I can see how much my unit testing provides, compare that to what I have left to test, and then make a judgement on where to go from there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Devising my Unit Testing Philosophy]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/10/devising-my-unit-testing-philosophy/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-10T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/10/devising-my-unit-testing-philosophy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Up to now my approach to unit testing has been dictated by who I was writing the code for. For instance in college I never wrote unit tests. In the real world some of my employers required unit testing, with certain branch and code coverage goals, while other employers didn’t require much in the way of unit testing, as long as other types of testing were carried out. In practice I found that the as the code became more lower level, the demands for unit tests increased.</p>

<p>For this project I need to define for myself what level of testing I will perform. My initial assumption was that of course I would do unit testing. Personally I thought that the benefits of unit testing were</p>

<ul>
<li>the confidence that it gives me in my code. I know that I can call this piece of code from somewhere else and there is a high probability that it will work as intended.</li>
<li>by catching errors at an early stage, I spend less time in the debugger later.</li>
<li>refactoring should go easier as the unit tests will catch a lot of regression issues</li>
<li>I can be confident that any new bugs will be in the new code rather than the older highly unit tested modules, thus cutting down the amount of code required to search in order to fix the bug.</li>
</ul>


<p>However I read an interesting and thought provoking <a href="http://wilshipley.com/blog/2005/09/unit-testing-is-teh-suck-urr.html" title="">article</a> by Will Shipley outlining why he doesn’t do unit testing. My immediate reaction was astonishment. How can you not have unit tests? However instead of unit tests, he beta tests the product. This finds the type of bugs that the actual end users will find. Also he writes his code in a manner that doesn’t require unit tests.</p>

<blockquote><p>My programming philosophy is “less code is better code.” Unit tests take a lot of code, and in my projects I don’t find that they find very many bugs. Part of this is because I tend not to modify my individual methods much once they’ve been written; if my “append string to string” method works, it’s really not going to get revisited anytime soon unless it has a bug.
Part of it is because, in fact, I do do integrated testing of a form, and I probably should have talked about that more. Yes, I use “NSAssert” all over the place, and I perform sanity checks and raise errors if there’s a problem.</p></blockquote>

<p>I don’t think I’ve come across “Not modifying methods once they are written” before but looking at it now it makes sense. By not changing existing working methods and treating them as black boxes, we should have fewer regression errors in future. I’m not sure how to reconcile this with refactoring though - it’s something to think about. I’d imagine a coding style that favours smaller, more focused methods would be more suited to this approach.</p>

<p>His use of sanity checks and asserts also struck a chord especially when he says</p>

<blockquote><p>Debugging most errors, once found, should take very little time in a properly-written program, because the error should always be from one of your own sanity checks, and you know where those are in the code, so you just go there and figure out what went wrong.</p></blockquote>

<p>This was eye-opening for me. I’ve never tracked this before so I’m not sure if the bugs I’ve written have evaded my sanity checks and asserts. I would imagine a lot of them did. I’d never have seen that as important before but looking at it now it seems to me that this is a failure on my behalf. Not catching these errors means that I’m not fully aware of how my code can go wrong and what it is doing in all cases. I think a useful analysis I should run on each bug I find is - did this escape my coding checks/asserts and if so why? I should learn from this and in future code should check for this condition.</p>

<p>In a response to Will’s article, a <a href="http://www.friday.com/bbum/2005/09/24/unit-testing">follow up post</a> by bbum shows how unit testing was of great benefit on infrastructure code, in this case the <a href="http://developer.apple.com/macosx/coredata.html">Core Data</a> library. This would suggest to me that the utility and model code would be amenable to unit testing but that it’s not useful for the GUI code.</p>

<p>Another <a href="http://blog.codeville.net/2009/08/24/writing-great-unit-tests-best-and-worst-practises/">article</a> on codeville challenged my assumptions that unit tests were about finding bugs. Instead the type of testing that finds bugs is manual testing or automated integration testing. According to him, unit testing is not about finding bugs (except during refactoring) but more about designing robust software components.</p>

<blockquote><p>TDD is a design process, not a testing process. TDD is a robust way of designing software components (“units”) interactively so that their behaviour is specified through unit tests
Also it’s not enough to just write unit tests. The tests need to be either true unit tests which design a single component or else integration tests which automate the entire system. Anything in between are
dirty hybrids. Unclear goal. High maintenance, don’t prove much
Otherwise when we refactor code, we end up breaking lots of seemingly unrelated hybrid tests. If you change a unit, then its unit tests should change but no other unit tests should.</p></blockquote>

<p>After all that I’ve decided that I want to do some level of unit testing but I realize that I need to focus it on the right areas. I think it will be useful for the utility type code that I write but that I need to do more research into how I want to implement integration testing and UI testing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Objective C Categories and Monkey Patching]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/04/objective-c-categories-and-monkey-patching/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-04T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/02/04/objective-c-categories-and-monkey-patching</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of my favorite features of Objective C are <a href="http://developer.apple.com/library/ios/#documentation/cocoa/conceptual/objectivec/chapters/occategories.html">categories</a>. Categories allow you to add your own functionality to existing classes without the need for inheritance. You don&#8217;t even need the source code of the modified class. You are only allowed add extra methods or modify existing methods. Adding extra instance variables is not permitted. This feature is generally known as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monkey_patch">monkey patching</a> (what a great name!) in languages such as Ruby.</p>

<p>Creating a category is straightforward. The interface and implementation files look the same as normal interface and implementation files except the category name is placed in brackets after the name of the class we are extending. For example to create a category MyCategory on MyClass the interface file looks like</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>MyClass+MyCategory.h  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='objc'><span class='line'><span class="cp">#import &quot;MyClass.h&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">@interface</span> <span class="nc">MyClass</span> <span class="nl">(MyCategory)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// Declare Methods here</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">@end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>and the implementation like this</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span>MyClass+MyCategory.m  </span></figcaption>
 <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='objc'><span class='line'><span class="cp">#import &quot;MyClass+MyCategory.h&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">@implementation</span> <span class="nc">MyClass</span> <span class="nl">(MyCategory)</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="c1">// Implement methods here</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="k">@end</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The standard naming convention for category files is ClassToExtend+Category.(h|m). So for the above we would have both MyClass+MyCategory.h and MyClass+MyCategory.m files. The header file needs to be imported in any file that uses the category. For common extensions we can place them in the precompiled header (pch) files.</p>

<p>This has a number of applications. It allows you to add methods to classes (or indeed to alter existing methods) instead of having to create utility classes comprised of static methods. Thus the code is more clearly associated with the class to which it belongs. It allows you to create object-oriented code that favours composition over inheritance.</p>

<p>To give a concrete example, for my current project I wanted to be able to shuffle an array. Instead of having to create a ShuffleableArray subclass or implement an ArrayUtils.shuffle helper method, I was able to add a shuffle method to the NSArray type via a category.</p>

<p>Not only does the class to which you add the category get the new method, but all its subclasses gain the method also. This can be very useful if you are extending a class high up in the hierarchy. For example, another use I made of categories was to add debug methods to the UIView class e.g. to print data about itself and its subviews. Given that lots of the UI widget classes extend UIView this means that everything on screen got my new methods. I find trace methods like these very useful during unit testing and debugging. I tend to prefer adding print code where possible rather than step through the debugger, and for that case the ability to add functionality to existing classes is invaluable.</p>

<p>Naturally like all programming language features categories can be greatly abused. Changing the behaviour of existing functions can break code which assumes the older behaviour. I&#8217;d imaging this would be especially so with system classes such as NSArray etc. However done right, they look like a very useful feature which I&#8217;m sure I&#8217;ll use a great deal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iTunes U and Online Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/29/itunes-u-and-online-learning/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-29T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/29/itunes-u-and-online-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Apple have just released the <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/ie/app/itunes-u/id490217893?mt=8">iTunes U app</a>. I think this has gotten a little lost compared to the attention on the new iBooks Author and its EULA. The iTunes U app looks to be an excellent app which puts some structure on the courses that were available through iTunes. Now you can watch the videos on your iPhone and iPad, and also download the slides to them. You can also use AirPlay to stream the videos to an Apple TV and the app will sync the progress of the course between devices.</p>

<p>The course I am currently looking at is the <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/ie/course/ipad-iphone-app-development/id495052415">Stanford iOS Programming course</a>. I&#8217;ve only seen the first few lectures but they are of excellent quality. There are about thirty of these new iTunes U courses at present but more should be added in the future.</p>

<p>While the talk was that the iBooks authoring app would revolutionize textbooks, I&#8217;m hopeful that the iTunes U app will do something similar for adult education. I&#8217;ve taken a few evening photography courses locally. These were great for me as a beginner but moving beyond that, it would be great to be able to subscribe to courses given by professionals. Remote learning can offer a wider range of courses than could ever be offered here in Cork. Courses that would be impractical to run locally due to small audiences don&#8217;t face that problem online. Imagine if you could subscribe to a landscape photography course with lectures by a series of landscape photographers. Or Portrait. Or Sports etc. And this would all come with slides that could be viewed afterwards at any time to refresh the memory.</p>

<p>Currently I&#8217;m looking into Graphic Design as I will need to create graphics for my app and I would like to do a course in this. However any real life courses would most likely not be suitable for me. I would need them to run in the evenings after work. Also I want a course that assumes I have lots of experience with computers. However what I&#8217;m more likely to find is a full time course aimed at school leavers which assumes no previous software experience. Remote learning offers the potential that multiple courses can be recorded, each aimed at different levels of experience. I could choose the one more suited to my circumstances and the scheduling would now not be an issue as I can do the course in my own free time.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s still early days but as more and more institutions put their courses up on iTunes U, I hope we start to see them not just put up their existing courses, but instead think about how they create and tailor courses for a wider audience. Although I&#8217;m not sure how likely that will be as currently the app doesn&#8217;t allow for paid courses. Still the free content is more than enough for the time being and I&#8217;ll look forward to see where iTunes U can go in the future.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> Just to clarify. The iTunes U app is separate from the desktop iTunes application. You can just download the iTunes U app on your device and never have to go near iTunes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessorizer for XCode]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/27/accessorizer-for-xcode/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-27T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/27/accessorizer-for-xcode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One thing about Objective C that struck me is the amount of boiler plate code that needs to be written for variables and methods. Ideally Xcode would handle all this but unfortunately it doesn&#8217;t.</p>

<p>An app I found to solve this problem is <a href="http://www.kevincallahan.org/software/accessorizer.html">Accessorizer</a>. It can generate interface and implementation for properties plus a whole range of other code (all that KVO and coding stuff that I haven&#8217;t looked into yet). It&#8217;s only 4 euro on the Mac App Store and it&#8217;s well worth it. There are some videos tutorials on the site which show you how much can be done with the program.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Version Control in Xcode using Git and Dropbox]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/26/version-control-in-xcode-using-git-and-dropbox/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-26T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/26/version-control-in-xcode-using-git-and-dropbox</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I first created projects in Xcode, I just let it take care of the version control for me by creating a Git local repository for my code. This was working fine for me but I could see that in future I would need more flexibility. I think it’s better to build that (and good programming habits in general) in at the start of a project when the codebase is small rather than refactoring down the line when it becomes a bigger problem.</p>

<p>One issue is that the local Git repository could only be used by one computer. If I wanted to share this code I would need to switch to using remote Git repositories. I also wanted to incorporate some form of remote backup for additional security.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.github.com">Github</a> (recommended to me by <a href="http://au.linkedin.com/pub/ian-hennessy/5/1b4/987">Ian Hennessy</a>) would do the job just fine but the free accounts are limited to public repositories. If I was working with other developers then it would make sense to pay for one of their plans. The collaboration tools e.g. issue tracking, code review look really good. It’s certainly a site I can see myself using in the future.</p>

<p>However for someone like me who is a solo developer, these features don’t add much value. I really just needed the backup functionality. So for this, I looked at storing the repository on <a href="http://www.dropbox.com">Dropbox</a>. It’s private and the free two gigabytes should be more than enough to host my code. Also Dropbox is available on pretty much everything and works well with firewalls. As for backups, it’s bullet proof. I’ve had my Windows PC hard drive fail recently. In the past this would have been a nightmare to deal with. Now I just installed a new drive, reinstalled Dropbox and saw all my documents reappear.</p>

<p>One issue that I think may arise would occur if Dropbox has conflicting edits on the same file from multiple locations. In that case I’d imagine it’s merge resolution would mess up the Git repository. Fortunately I don’t think that this will apply in this situation. I will be the only person with access to the repository and I won’t be editing the same files from two PCs at the same time.</p>

<p>To set up Dropbox I followed the steps on <a href="http://www.cimgf.com/2008/06/03/version-control-makes-you-a-better-programmer/">this</a> post from cimgf.com. This <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1960799/using-gitdropbox-together-effectively">answer</a> on StackOverflow is also a good reference.</p>

<ul>
<li>I created the project I wanted in Xcode and allowed it to set up a local Git Repository for me.</li>
<li>I cloned the repository using the bare keyword to a Dropbox location.
<code>git clone –-bare . ~/Dropbox/development/repositories/GCUtils/GCUtils.git</code>
The bare option is used as this will just clone the contents of the local .git directory to Dropbox. We don’t want to create a working copy of the code on Dropbox, as this may lead to Dropbox edit conflicts if that working copy is edited directly. In order to edit the code, a user should have to clone the repository to their machine, work on it locally and then push the changes to the Dropbox repository.</li>
<li>I created a remote alias.
<code>git remote add dbGCUtils ~/Dropbox/development/repositories/GCUtils/GCUtils.git</code></li>
<li>I restarted Xcode and in the repositories tab of the Organizer, it picked up the remote repository automatically.</li>
</ul>


<p>And that’s pretty much it for the initial setup. From here Xcode can manage the commits to the local repository and also the push and pull from the remote repository. The Xcode user guide describes how Xcode can interact with Git <a href="http://developer.apple.com/library/mac/#documentation/ToolsLanguages/Conceptual/Xcode4UserGuide/SCM/SCM.html">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Objective C]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/21/learning-objective-c/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-21T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/21/learning-objective-c</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here is a list of the resources I used when learning Objective C.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://developer.apple.com/library/ios/navigation/#section=Resource%20Types&amp;amp;topic=Getting%20Started">Apple Documentation</a>. This is really good, especially the Javadoc like pages for the UI classes. There are load of documents here. Ones that I missed first time around are the “Your First/Second/Third iOS App” guides. I’ll have to catch up on those. (One tip which I completely missed out on for ages. For these webpages, on the right hand side of the second toolbar, is a button which gets the whole doc as a PDF. It’s worth building up a library of these.) The two main documents that I used were

<ul>
<li><a href="http://developer.apple.com/library/ios/#documentation/UserExperience/Conceptual/MobileHIG/Introduction/Introduction.html">The Human Interface Guide</a>. This is a really excellent document for describing how to design an iOS app. It’s not code based but instead operates at a higher level explaining the UI principles and how the UI elements should be used.</li>
<li> <a href="http://developer.apple.com/library/ios/#documentation/Cocoa/Conceptual/ObjectiveC/Introduction/introObjectiveC.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP30001163">Objective C Programming Language</a>. I think this document is essential for learning Obejctive C. It details the extensions Objective C makes to the base C language and is really thorough.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> <a href="http://www.stackoverflow.com" title="">Stack Overflow</a>. This site is an absolute godsend. How did we ever live without it? The documents above are fine as an introduction to Objective C and app development. However when you start to create an app and run into practical issues, this site is fantastic. There has been no coding question that I have had that they haven’t been able to answer and the coding samples provided are normally top notch. I can’t recommend this site enough.</li>
<li>Google &amp; Blogs. In general searching for Objective C questions on google brings up a list of blogs which detail people’s practical implementations of various issues. These are useful to read as they normally contain any design decisions and reasons why alternatives were rejected.</li>
</ul>


<p>The main class of resources that I haven’t decided to use in learning Objective C have been books. There seem to be some good ones out there but I don’t think there’s much there that I haven’t been able to find on the web. Blogs and Stack Overflow have killed programming language books for me.</p>

<p>The other thing is that I think books about specific programming languages are the ones at risk of going out of date. My data structures and pattern books from college are still useful but any Java books from then have become outdated. The core object-oriented parts are still valid but you can say goodbye to vectors, Swing etc. I’ll have to keep an eye out for good Objective C pattern books.</p>

<p>To give a specific example, the ARC memory management recently introduced to Objective C has rendered the sample code in a lot of books obsolete. Not just obsolete but incorrect actually as the old code won’t compile with ARC enabled. On the web this can be updated, but the books are stuck with the older, invalid code. Maybe with ebooks becoming more popular there will be scope for having books that update their sample code automatically. Until then we have to wait for revised editions, if indeed they are released at all.</p>

<p>I just found <a href="http://chachatelier.fr/programmation/fichiers/cpp-objc-en.pdf">this</a> document (via <a href="http://www.twitter.com/steipete">@steipete</a>) which is a guide from C++ to Objective C. This looks to be really good.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beginning with Xcode]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/18/beginning-with-xcode/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-18T21:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/18/beginning-with-xcode</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The main application for developing apps is Xcode. I&#8217;m not sure if there are any alternatives but at the moment I don&#8217;t think I really need any. Xcode is free, installs from the app store. What more do I need?</p>

<p>Ok, so first I installed Xcode. Or rather I installed an installer for Xcode. Seems a bit odd. I&#8217;m not sure how that will work with updates from the Mac Store. At first glance it looked the same as most other editors. Text area for writing code, tree navigator for files etc. My initial impressions are that it should be straightforward to learn to use.</p>

<p>Onto learning how to create apps. My first stop was the tutorials on Ray Wenderlich&#8217;s <a href="http://www.raywenderlich.com/tutorials">site</a>. They&#8217;re really comprehensive and I really recommend them. I began with the iOS Apprentice free tutorial which teaches you how to create a game called Bullseye. From that I think I gained enough knowledge to find my way around Xcode. From here, time for the next step i.e. learning Objective C.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Choosing a language]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/14/choosing-a-language/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-14T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/01/14/choosing-a-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My initial thought was that I would obviously use Objective C to program the app. However a work colleague suggested that I look at <a href="http://www.appcelerator.com/">Appcelerator</a> as he had used it to create his app. (The app is for Irish Leaving Certificate students. It allows them to download past exam papers to their iPhone or iPad. If you&#8217;re a 5th or 6th year student check it out at <a href="http://www.jamessugrue.ie/app">http://www.jamessugrue.ie/app</a>.)</p>

<p>The technology basically allows you to use Javascript to create your application. This presumably will hide the lower level implementation details and allow you to create apps faster. Also the apps should be portable across mobile OSes so this would allow for Android ports.</p>

<p>I don&#8217;t think that this is the right approach for me though. I don&#8217;t know Javascript or much HTML5 so either way I&#8217;d have to learn a new language. My thinking is that Apple use Objective C and intend for it to be the official way to write apps. This means that there will be loads of help out there for writing in Objective C, e.g. Apple articles, books, Stack Overflow questions etc. One of my concerns is that when you start hitting road bumps in Appcelerator, I not sure there will be the same level of support available.</p>

<p>Another problem with these type of frameworks is that if Apple add new features, then you have to wait for your framework provider to update their product, to support the new features. In this case I think you&#8217;re better off using the standard language and APIs for the platform rather than a third party solution. Also the iPhone libraries seem fairly similar to the Mac libraries, so in future it should be straightforward enough to learn Mac programming after gaining an iOS foundation.</p>

<p>Given my C/C++ experience I think I will pick up Objective C quicker. I have no intention to support Android at this time so the cross platform support is not of any use to me. I&#8217;d also assume that, as most apps are developed in Objective C, that this will be more in demand by employers in future. So, Objective C it is then. How hard can it be&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
