<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Business | Gerard Condon's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/categories/business/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-22T23:29:30+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerard Condon]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Start your own Business Course]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/03/20/start-your-own-business-course/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-20T23:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerardcondon.com/blog/2012/03/20/start-your-own-business-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've signed up for a Start Your Own Business <a href="http://www.sceb.ie/Online-Booking#Start-Your-Own-Business">course</a> which is being run by the <a href="http://www.sceb.ie">South Cork Enterprise Board</a>. It's an eight week course taking three hours every Thursday. I've no intention of leaving my current job but if I'm going to be doing this on the side, then I'd like to know how to do it properly and what type of supports are out there.</p>

<p>I've gone to three nights already and I'm finding it very useful. I think that the process of creating a business plan focuses your mind on what you want to achieve. I've asked myself more questions about what I want to do with this app development in the past few weeks than in the previous two months. It's also interesting meeting people there who are setting up non software businesses and seeing what common problems and tasks we have. It's good to step outside the software/computing world for a bit and get a wider perspective on things. I hope to come out of this with a clear idea of where I want to take the app work and what I need to do to accomplish this.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
